<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To the most honorable the Council of State, the humble petition of Captain William Jackett, and his partners</title>
            <author>Jackett, William.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1650</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 11 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A87548</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J62A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R179171</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">45504481</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 45504481</idno>
            <idno type="VID">171797</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A87548)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 171797)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2591:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>To the most honorable the Council of State, the humble petition of Captain William Jackett, and his partners</title>
                  <author>Jackett, William.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>7 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1650?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Date and place of publication suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Sutro Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jackett, William.</term>
               <term>Shipping --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Slave traders --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Foreign relations --  Spain --  1625-1649 --  Sources.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="petition">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:171797:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO The moſt Honorable THE Council of State, The humble Petition of Captain <hi>William Jackett,</hi> and his Partners.</head>
            <opener>Sheweth,</opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat whereas the humble Petitioners were in the year 1648 (ſince this Sate was reduced into a Commonwealth) moſt unjuſtly and inhumanely dealt withal by the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> and his Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers; and eſpecially, by the moſt diſloyal proceedings of <hi>Don Franciſco Baracall de Campo,</hi> who, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to the Laws of Nations, deprived them of the value of threeſcore thouſand pound ſterling, as it is more at large ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in the annexed Relation.</p>
            <p>Moreover, whereas the truth of their Caſe is evidently apparant by authentick proofs, under the Signatures of Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Notaries, the which your humble Petitioners have to produce; and that they cannot obtain any juſtice at all: for that their Ships and Specialties have been diſpoſed of to the ſaid King's uſe, whereby their Caſe is rendered moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperate: Beſides, the barbarous impriſonments which they ſuffered, and where they might have periſhed, had they not by providence made an eſcape.</p>
            <p>So it is, that your humble Petitioner having found a way whereby this Commonwealth may right them, by ſuch
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:171797:2"/>
means as are moſt conſonant to this Commonwealth's equitie and power; on ſuch juſt preſidents as were made uſe of in Queen <hi>Eliſabeth</hi>'s time, and the ſame which are to this day practiſed by the <hi>Spaniards</hi> themſelvs, the <hi>French, Danes,</hi> and <hi>Hollanders, viz.</hi> by this Commonwealth's allotting unto your humble Petitioner a ſatisfaction out of ſuch effects as are in this Commonwealths poſſeſſion, and the which do belong unto the <hi>Spaniards.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, whereas this State is at preſent poſſeſſed of ſuch monies and effects, as appertain unto divers Spaniſh Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of thoſe parts of the <hi>Indies,</hi> where your humble Petitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners ſuſtained their ſaid loſſes: The which monies and effects were brought up hither by one Captain <hi>Stafford,</hi> Commander of the Ship <hi>Sancta Clara</hi> from S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Domingo;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Your humble Petitioners therefore crave, That the monies at preſent claimed by the Spaniſh Embaſſador, and other his Maſter's ſubjects, may by your Honor's order be applied to the Petitioner's re-imburſment; And that the King of <hi>Spain</hi> may bee left to give ſatisfaction unto his Subjects with your Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titioner's monies and effects, ſo unjuſtly taken and detained from them, on a pretended occaſion, without any example.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>And they ſhall ever pray, &amp;c.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:171797:2"/>
            <head>The State of Captain <hi>William Jackett</hi>'s, and his Partner's Caſe.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>ANno</hi> 1647. <hi>Will. Jackett</hi> Commander of the <hi>May-flower,</hi> a Ship of 400 Tuns and 30 pieces of Ord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, together with the <hi>Peter</hi> of 100 Tuns and ten pieces of Ordnance (being laden with ſeveral marchandize) ſet ſail from <hi>London</hi> the 16<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>June,</hi> and arrived in <hi>Guiny</hi> in the Month of <hi>September</hi> following, where the ſaid Captain <hi>Jackett</hi> bought 460 <hi>Negro's</hi> or <hi>Blacks,</hi> intending to ſell them where hee beſt might: But touching at the <hi>Barbado's,</hi> hee there met with one <hi>Don Lewis de Chaves,</hi> a Subject of the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> unto whom the ſaid King of <hi>Spain</hi> had granted a free Licence for to freight any Ship of what Nation ſoëver, that was in peace with the Crown of <hi>Spain,</hi> for to tranſport <hi>Negro's</hi> into the <hi>Indies;</hi> whereupon Captain <hi>Jackett</hi> made an agreement with the ſaid <hi>Don Lewis de Chaves</hi> to go with him into the <hi>Indies;</hi> and by the ſaid agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the ſaid <hi>Don Lewis de Chaves</hi> was bound to enter the ſaid Captain <hi>Jackett</hi>'s <hi>Negro's</hi> in the ſaid Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence with his own, which accordingly was don: And on the 25 of <hi>March,</hi> they arrived in the <hi>Weſt-Indies,</hi> where beeing com to an anchor, were permitted to com on ſhoar, where they met the Governour and the reſt of the King of <hi>Spain</hi>'s Officers of that place, unto whom <hi>Don Lewis</hi> preſented his Licence, the which when as the ſaid Governor <hi>Franciſco Baracall de Campo</hi> Captain-General of the Province of <hi>Catilonia,</hi> and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor of <hi>Barſilonia</hi> in the <hi>Indies</hi> had peruſed, hee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:171797:3"/>
thereof as a thing legal and valid, demanding of Cap. <hi>Jackett</hi> what Countriman, and whence hee was; who made anſwer, That hee was an Engliſhman, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitant of <hi>London,</hi> and that hee came thither freighted by <hi>Don Lewis de Chaves,</hi> to Trade there by virtue of that Licence the King of <hi>Spain</hi> had granted unto <hi>Don Lewis de Chaves;</hi> on the which, if ſo bee hee could bee received and admitted, to Trade with them hee would: but if the contrary, hee would preſently bee gone his waies.</p>
            <p>Unto which declaration of Capt. <hi>Jackett</hi>'s the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor replied, That <hi>Don Lewis</hi> his Licence ſhould bee conſidered of the next day in their Council, and if as then they found it legal or valid (as hee ſuppoſed the ſame to bee) they would give him their poſitive an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer whether or no hee might bee received, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to Trade.</p>
            <p>According whereunto the chief Officers of the ſaid Council, together with the Maior of the ſaid Town, did the next day (by the Governor's order) com and viſit or ſearch the ſaid Cap. <hi>Jackett</hi>'s Ships, telling him that hee might on the above-ſaid Licence (which they had found to bee verie good and true) freely Trade amongſt them; whereupon they took a Regiſter of what <hi>Negro's</hi> and goods the ſaid Cap. <hi>Jackett</hi> had aboard his two Ships, to the end, that ſuch Cuſtom, as belonged to the King of <hi>Spain</hi> in thoſe parts, might bee paid; the which the ſaid Capt. <hi>Jackett</hi> immediately paid.</p>
            <p>Moreover, the ſaid aſſurance thus given in the King's name to Trade freely there, and the Cuſtom paid, the ſaid Cap. <hi>Jackett</hi> proceeded to cut <hi>Braſielleto</hi> wood, and to buy Hides and Tobacco, and ſuch other Commodities as the Countrie afforded, and were requiſite to lade his Ships withal, continuing thus in his ſaid trafficking for
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:171797:3"/>
the ſpace of near nine months; at the exſpiration where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, the aforeſaid Governor conceiving that the ſaid Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>Jackett</hi> might bee ready to ſet ſail, hee as then cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted his Chirurgion, and about fortie more of his men; with whom hee made a Covenant to betray in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his hands the ſaid Captain <hi>Jackett</hi>'s perſon, and chief Officers, together with his ſhips, and lading, for ſuch a ſumme of monie as hee had contracted for, and obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged himſelf to give them, the which they received; and accordingly delivered up the ſaid Captain <hi>Jackett,</hi> his ſhip, and goods, amounting to the value of three-ſcore thouſand pound ſterling, into the ſaid Governor's hand, notwithſtanding their former and formal decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and free admittance of Trade in thoſe parts, by virtue of the afore-mentioned <hi>Don Lewis</hi> his Licence, contrarie to the which, hee had not acted any thing.</p>
            <p>Finally, by this unjuſt proceeding in the ſaid Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, both the ſaid Captain <hi>Jackett,</hi> and his ſaid Partners were undon, after the ſaid Captain <hi>Jackett</hi> had in his own perſon ſuffered many extremities, during his deten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in priſon, where hee had periſhed, had hee not by Providence been aſſiſted to make an eſcape.</p>
            <p>All which appeareth by the Spaniards own papers, autorized by their own publick Notaries.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:171797:4"/>
            <head>An Abbreviate of ſuch Arguments as the STATE may bee pleaſed to make uſe of, in the behalf of the aforeſaid Captain <hi>William Jackett,</hi> and his Partner's Plea.</head>
            <p>IN the firſt place, That the wrongs which the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards have don unto Captain <hi>William Jackett</hi> were during this Parlament's Aſſembling; and that the ſaid <hi>Don Franciſco de Baracall de Campo</hi> did corrupt the ſaid Captain <hi>Jackett</hi> his men, for to deliver up unto him the ſaid Captain's ſhips, and goods, out of a ſpleen to the Parlament, declaring to the Governor, that the ſaid Captain was ſent as a ſpie, to ſee their Countrie, that hee might the better com with a Fleet by the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lament's order to take their Countrie from them: on which report the Captain was ordered to be hanged in the market place, but on better conſideration, after they had heard him ſpeak, was onely ſent priſoner to <hi>Spain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In regard whereof the ſaid Captain his ſhips and goods were converted to the King of <hi>Spain</hi>'s uſe:</p>
            <p>Whereby the ſaid Captain <hi>Jackett</hi> his Caſe differ's from all others, who before that time were wronged by the Spaniards.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that all other Captains, or Sea-faring men, who paſt the Line, went thither on their own perils,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:171797:4"/>
which was not ſo with Captain <hi>Jackett,</hi> for that hee was freighted by <hi>Don Lewis de Chaves,</hi> a ſubject to the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> whoſe Licence was alſo acknowledged by the ſaid King's Governors in the Indies: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the ſaid Captain paied him in the Cuſtoms as then due.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, that the King of <hi>Spain</hi> hath on ſeveral oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, ſeized on ſtrangers goods, on unjuſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, even in his own Ports, as alſo the <hi>French,</hi> the <hi>Danes,</hi> and others have don:</p>
            <p>In ſomuch that the ſaid Captain <hi>Jackett</hi> his Caſe dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering from all other, doth the more argue (for that it is impoſsible for him and his Partners to obtein ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction from the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> far leſs from the ſaid <hi>Franciſco Baracall de Campo,</hi> who is a Governor in the Indies) that therefore this State cannot reſolv upon a piece of Juſtice more conſonant to their own honor, and the merit of the Caſe, then to right the ſaid Captain <hi>Jackett,</hi> and his Partners, by allotting them right and ſatisfaction out of the monies which are at preſent claimed by the Spaniſh Embaſſadors, in the behalf of his Maſters, and his Subjects.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
